Hello. Uh, my name is Derek Rdney and
I'm a pastor in Winston Salem, North
Carolina at Trinity Church PCA and I'm
hosting this conversation today on
behalf of the Alliance for Mission and
Renewal. The Alliance exists uh to help
foster a you a unified, faithful, and
flourishing PCA. We're an organization
dedicated to assisting and encouraging
churches, ministry leaders, and all our
PCA sisters and brothers in the work of
communicating the gospel of Jesus Christ
in our cultural moment. Uh we like to
celebrate and share stories of the
beautiful ways that God is working in
and through our denomination. Uh my
conversation today is with the Reverend
Charles McGawan. Uh he is an advisory
board member of A4MR.
Charles uh was ordained more than 55
years ago and is now the pastor
emmeritus at Christ Presbyterian in
Nashville. Uh he served as the moderator
of three presbyteries and in 1996 he was
the moderator of the general assembly
that met in Fort Lauderdale, Florida. He
continues to serve the church today
through uh the McGawan Global Institute,
which he founded in 2008 and which seeks
to help churches thrive through
resourcing uh revitalization and
coaching. Charles was married to Alice
for more than 58 years before her death.
And he has four children and 21
grandchildren and great-g
grandandchildren. So, Charles, uh thanks
for joining me today. It's a pleasure to
have you. Well, it's a joy for me to be
here with you, uh, Derek. And, u I, uh,
I was startled when you numbered my
children and great-grandchildren and
grandchildren. That's quite a
quite a trail that I'm leaving behind
me.
>> Yeah, that's a wonderful legacy and, uh,
just a great blessing, I'm sure. Uh,
well, today, um, I was hoping that we
could talk about the history of the PCA,
which I've I've done recently a
recording with, uh, Dr. Sean Lucas on
the history of the PCA as a historian,
but with you, I would really love to get
your perspective as as one of the few
fathers of the PCA that's still alive
today, uh, who was there, who lived our
history on the ground, was part of the
meetings and conversations and really
saw the birth of the PCA and then has
lived, uh, his life as a minister uh, in
the PCA since then. And so just hoping
to get some of the the sort of animating
concerns that that drove the founding of
the PCA and then what were the hopes and
dreams of of the various men and women
who were part of that conversation. So
part of the reason I'm doing this and I
said this in our last uh interview is
that there kind of are different
narratives about the PCA that exists
right now. One of them is that we we
started out in sort of a a faithful way
uh a sort of rigorously reformed
denomination and we've just been sliding
for 50 years into a more compromised
liberal or loose denomination. And then
um others see the denomination as being
founded as a sort of broadly reformed
evangelical conservative mainline
denomination that has um sort of become
more reformed in many ways and has kind
of maintained this breadth with
different groups within the reformed
tradition working together on mission to
plant churches and reach the nations
with the gospel. And so, uh, in some
ways, this history project is really
intended to just, uh, let people get a
sense of where we've come from and
where, um, that might shape where we're
going. So, um, in in that sense, I'd
love to just hear your story. Um, I'm
just going to ask questions. Love to
hear you talk about your experience with
the PCA. So, maybe it would help to just
start with you saying how you came to
know the Lord. you know, what was your
church background uh before the PCA was
formed and and then how did that shape
your sort of entry into the PCA?
>> Well, that's uh that's a good way to
begin, I think, Derek, because um I'm
currently in the process of writing my
memoirs just for my family. It's going
to be a private published kind of a of a
document book for for my children and
grandchildren and great-grandchildren.
But, uh, when I tell my story, it's
really the story of of growing up in a
in in poverty really in, uh, eastern
North Carolina on a tobacco farm, a
spare small tobacco farm that my father
inherited from his father, uh, Macdonald
McGowan. And, um, and um, uh, as far as
I can tell, neither my mother nor my
father ever got active at all in a
church. Though my um genealological
record indicates that my uh paternal
grandparents and great-grandparents and
great great-grandparents had a
relationship with a primitive Baptist
church, which is a hyperreformed
Baptist uh denomination, which is
gradually fading out because they don't
believe in missions and evangelism.
They're that Calvinistic.
And um
and so for the first 15 18 years of
their marriage, uh there was no
involvement in church as far as I can
tell. Um
uh except for weddings and funerals,
they probably set foot in a church. But
uh I was born in the height of the
depression in 1936.
Um and um and I was born into a family
that was struggling economically. We had
no car. We had no electricity. We had no
plumbing. We had a a hand pump. And we
were we were living in a home that my
grandfather uh had built himself. He was
a carpenter. A comfortable home, but it
was a very primitive home really. And
with a wood burning heater and a wood
burning cook stove and and those kinds
of things. And and as children were
born, one after the other, I'm the
seventh of seven children. Uh pressures
only increased in our family. and uh uh
fear of losing the farm through the
depression was all was really much very
much a part of that. Plus the fact my
dad was uh he grew up in a dysfunctional
family and was never really given lots
of training and um held responsible or
held accountable for his his lifestyle
and so
uh he actually dropped out of school at
the end of the second grade. So he
became an illiterate person for the rest
of his life.
>> Could not even write his name. And but
my story is important to give you that
kind of a backdrop because uh my mother
was a very strong and and um committed
woman. Uh she was committed to the
marriage. Uh she had a a strong maternal
uh loving uh instinct about her and I
think the marriage got increasingly
difficult for her. Um and um and I think
she began to have a hunger for help from
the outside. Where can I find help to
sustain myself? And one day she
announced to my dad, I I don't know
about you, but I am going to start going
to church with my children.
And um by that time, it was probably
um when she made that declaration. And
by that time, he had bought a used 1936
four-door Chevrolet sedan.
>> And he agreed to take us to church. And
interestingly, Derek, we we uh she chose
for us to go to a freewheel baptist
church. Can you imagine that?
>> Very common in that part of the of the
state.
>> That's right. And it was called the
Blackjack Freewheel Baptist Church
because it was in a crossroads called
the Blackjack uh crossroads, a little
community about 5 milesi from my home
which you could only reach by uh what my
dad called a washboard dirt road. And um
and so he by the time he finally got to
the church on a on a Sunday morning, he
was in a bad mood. He would drop us off
at the church and walk across the dirt
road and and spend the time in the
country store talking farming and
politics and smoking his pipe and um and
then after church was over uh we would
all gather in the car again and managed
to get all seven of us plus mom and dad
in that car and um and we would go home
and and that went on probably for a year
and then the blackjack threw a Baptist
church announced that they were having
their annual revival and my mother said,
"I want to go to that." And uh so my
daddy, but I I don't recall any of the
children going, but my daddy took her
and she may not have gone to all the
meetings, but on the Friday night of
that meeting, she walked down the aisle
of that Free Will Baptist Church and
made a commitment of her life to Christ.
and and the following Sunday um she was
to be baptized in the in the Torah River
which runs through that community
>> and little town called Grimesland.
>> And um and so we went went home from
church and then we had lunch and u and
then she dressed appropriately for the
baptism, however that was. And she
gathered all the children around her and
she said, "Children, your daddy's going
to take me to Grimes to get baptized. I
made a commitment last Friday night um
to accept Jesus Christ as my savior and
to follow him as my lord and um
and uh in obedience to Jesus Christ. I'm
being baptized
and I know this is going to be a
difficult thing for me to follow Christ
and I need your help. So I want you to
understand that I'm seeking to begin a
new life, a new relationship with God.
And she said, "And by the way, if the
sane is operating, the sane was the
place where fish were netted and sold
commercially. If the sane is operating,
your dad is going to buy a mess of fish
and we're going to invite the preacher
who baptizes me to dinner this evening."
And uh and it all happened that way. The
preacher came, we had a a wonderful
fried dish dinner. And um and I I never
got word that any of the children were
disciplined for misbehaving. And so that
was the way the Christian life began for
her. And um
and we continued to uh to attend that
that church. Now she's a baptized member
of that church. But my dad was watching
all of this and he himself was
miserable. And God began to work in his
life because he took her to be baptized.
He would take her to church and he began
to observe her life as a as a Christian.
and u but providentially sovereignly we
might say
um first Presbyterian Church
um in in Greenville, North Carolina,
which was the town nearest our farm uh
was started in a little mission Sunday
school in our neighborhood in a two-
room schoolhouse which my older siblings
went to school in
>> Hollywood school because it was located
in a Holly Grove and um and they were
having a Sunday afternoon mission Sunday
school. That's the way they did church
planting back in those days. They would
start a Sunday school and then the
people from the church would volunteer
to go and teach the Sunday school after
their Sunday lunch. They would go out on
Sunday afternoon at 2:00 and teach
Sunday school. And the way they promoted
it that they would have uh a Bible
school every summer and then say, "We're
going to continue doing this on
Sundays." And uh so um come come and
join us on Sunday and we'll just
continue this. And so the little thing,
little Sunday school grew to be a a
healthy little mission. And um and we
began to get students from Union
Seminary and Colombia Seminary to come
in the summer and help out. and and um
and but one day the pastor uh First
Presbyterian Church uh who who made a
practice of coming to that community
every Thursday afternoon and going from
home to farm to farm to farm to um to
share Christ and publicize the Sunday
school and uh I don't think the family
even knew that that Sunday school
existed but he came to the to our farm
and uh knocked on the screen door to the
back porch church and my mother went to
the screen door and she uh he introduced
herself and said he was the pastor of
First Presbyterian Church. His name was
Dr. Robert Boyd, B O Y D. And uh a godly
man had a real vision for church
planting. And um this was one of about
three or four of these missions that he
had started in or around Greenville.
>> And um and he he asked he asked my
mother, "Is Mr. McGowan at home. And she
said, "Well, he's not here in the house,
but he's plowing. If you look across up
in the field, you'll you'll see him with
two mules and and a plow." And um that's
where he is. And so that pastor dressed
up with coat and tie and a hat and um
made his way across freshly plowed
ground uh to my daddy.
>> And um and my daddy welcomed him and he
talked to my daddy about the Sunday
school. And then he said, "I'm here
really here to tell you about a
wonderful good news. Uh, Mr. McGowan,
I'm here to tell you that God has
arranged for you to have a wonderful
gift, the gift of eternal life." And he
went through the gospel with my daddy
and he said, "Now, Mr. McGan, would you
like to have that gift?" And he said,
"Dad," my daddy said, "Yes, I'd like to
have that gift." And he said, "Well, you
must receive it." And you receive it by
praying and accepting it. And so my dad
got on his knees, put his head against
the steel beam of the prowl, and and
gave his heart to Jesus.
>> I'm sure my mother was back at the
farmhouse praying.
>> And when daddy came home that evening,
she probably quizzed him about what the
preacher talked about. And he probably
reluctantly told her about, well, he was
talking about the missions Sunday
school. And he also told me about Jesus.
and she kept proddding him and he
finally she finally he finally told her
that I I'll pray and receive Christ as
my savior. Well, the very next Sunday we
were at the Sunday school at Hollywood
School and and he was the first elder uh
ordained in that church and uh was an
elder in that church for over 60 years.
>> He lived to be 99.
>> Wow. And uh uh it's a wonderful story
because
it's a it's a story of God's sovereign
providence.
Uh and my mother immediately became
identified with the Presbyterian church.
And uh and uh our family would go to
that church every Sunday. And uh and and
that and that
that experience uh Derek brought light
and life to my mother and my father and
to my family and to the community and
radically changed as Tim Keller often
said, "The gospel changes everything.
>> It changed my mother and dad just
personally. It changed their marriage.
It changed our family. And uh and just
to show you the practical ways uh uh my
sister, my oldest sister who was 14 when
I was born was encouraged by Robert Boyd
to go to college because she was such a
good student. She would be she was the
first
uh girl, the first child in our
community to ever go to college.
>> And um and so people were amazed at
that. How can Lonnie McGowan in afford
that? And and yet Robert Boyd explained
that the college would give her
a scholarship and she could have a work
scholarship and it really wouldn't cost
them anything for her to go to college.
>> And u and the long story is every one of
the seven children went to college,
graduated from college and and myself
and my brother both became Presbyterian
pastors.
>> Wow.
>> So it's it's kind of a it's kind of an
encouraging story. And so
>> definitely
>> and so that uh that story became that
church became a strong evangelical rule
church
>> in the southern Presbyterian church.
Yeah.
>> Was before the PCA was everformed.
>> Yeah.
>> So your so your way into the into the
PCA, you know, in in one sense came
through the evangelism of a Presbyterian
minister to your family and and that's
how you guys got connected.
>> Exactly. And uh and when my brother came
back from World War II, he had had a
fresh encounter with Jesus through the
Navigators at Pearl Harbor. And uh and
he came back from the war, committed to
prepare himself to be a pastor. Went to
Davidson College and then went to
Columbia Seminary. And uh he and Kennedy
Smart were roommates at Davidson and
very close friends for as long as my
brother lived. He lived to be 98. Wow.
And um
and so um so we I we have pretty deep
roots,
>> right? Yeah. Now you went to Davidson
College as well, right? And did you go
directly into seminary after that? How
did you get into the ministry?
Well, I um I went to Davis in college
and I felt really from high school days
that God was calling me to be a pastor.
But it was a real struggle for me,
Derek, because my brother's shadow was
so uh was so deep and so vivid and I I
was fearful that I was only thinking
that because I admired my brother so
much
>> and um
and and then my image of being a pastor
was a very negative image. I I could
only see him wearing black and standing
in front of caskets doing funerals and
and those kinds of things. I I saw
nothing nothing dynamic or exciting
about the work for pastor. Mhm.
>> And so, um, when I graduated from
Davidson, while I had applied to
Columbia Seminary to go to school, I
didn't show up, uh, largely because I
had taken ROTC in college and I had an
army obligation. And, uh, so that gave
me an excuse to, uh, to put off the
decision to go to seminary. And um and
so after I finished my Army obligation,
I continued that career with the Office
of Naval Intelligence and became a
special agent with Office of Naval
Intelligence as a civilian uh for a
number of years as well. And so I was
late in my 20s when I actually wound up
going off to seminary.
>> Okay. And um and I I wound up going to
Columbia Seminary at a kind of an
unfortunate time because Columbia
Seminary was was becoming um heavily
influenced by neo orthodoxy and
guardianism.
>> Which today looks pretty conservative
against the backdrop of of of modern
theology. But but um
>> what year was this, Charles? in 63. I I
my wife and I were living in Washington
DC and I was working with O and Office
of Naval Intelligence and and uh a year
earlier we had gotten on our knees and
given our lives to Christian ministry uh
vocationally
and um and I spent the year making
choices as to what seminary I was going
to and things of this sort. You know, on
August the 28th, the day that Martin
Luther King made his famous speech on
the steps of the Lincoln Memorial,
we listened to the speech and our
Volkswagen uh bug as we left Washington
DC for Atlanta, Georgia for to enroll in
in Columbia Seminary. M
>> and um and I enrolled and um and people
in my class were people like Wilson
Benton and um um
Paul Cor was a year behind me and
>> of that generation, but I was older. I
was older and because I I'd come late
>> and u
and we had a a wonderful um uh
fellowship of conservative evangelical
students there and so much so that the
president on uh at the beginning of the
year said to us
um I want to tell you that you're on
trial here not the faculty of this
school
>> and uh in other words you behave
yourself uh and let the faculty teach
you.
>> And um and so we really had a somewhat
of a struggle. Um but we had a wonderful
fellowship uh with some wonderful
professors like uh Manfred Goodsky and
William Charles Robinson and others who
were still faithful to historic reformed
uh Christianity.
>> Yeah. So you were experiencing some of
the tensions that were growing in the
PCUs in seminary. you were you were a
conservative evangelical and feeling
that tension that was brewing in the
denomination as a whole.
>> Yeah, I had really I had really
experienced that um during my high
school years because
um a a a group of there was an effort
back in the I think it was back in the
uh mid to late 50s to merge the northern
church and the southern church. and some
of the some of the concerned layman
uh led by Nelson Bell, Dr. Nelson Bell,
Billy Graham's father-in-law,
and Henry Dendy and u um and and other
other um uh other well-known layman in
in the southern church. The southern
church was drifting and I knew it was
drifting even from high school years.
And um I remember Dr. bell being hosted
by First Presbyterian Church in
Greenville to lecture on why we should
vote down uh the proposal to merge with
the UPCUSA
and um I think it was called the PCUSA
then I'm not sure which it was the
northern church we thought it was the
northern church
>> and and I remember him saying some
people are accusing us of trying to
split the church he said let me tell you
it's impossible to split this church
because you can't split a rotten log
M
>> and I remember that vividly and I was
just in high school in those days and so
I was very much aware of it and then
during during um my seminary years there
was a big controversy about women's
ordination which
>> uh allowed for women preachers etc. And
so and then there became a concerned
Presbyterians and Presbyterian Churchmen
United and all kinds of conservative
evangelical uh movements trying to stem
the tide of liberalism.
>> Yeah. So you were following those
conversations. You were you were aware
of what was going on. You were getting
into ministry right as there was more
and more talk about where are we going?
How do we stop this? What is this going
to be?
>> Yeah. Back during seminary days, I would
go to the annual Presbyterian Journal
meeting up in Weaverville, North
Carolina, which today is World Magazine,
but but uh that would be an annual
rallying point. And um and then when I
was ordained and became a pastor, I
immediately identified with Presbyterian
Churchmen United, which was an
organization led by Don Patterson and a
few others. Uh Don was pastor of First
Church, Jackson, Mississippi in those
days. And I became kind of a errand boy
for uh for the for the uh for the troops
for the older pastors in the and we we
formed a coalition u uh Presbyterian
Churchman United, Presbyterian
Evangelistic Fellowship, Concerned
Presbyterian, which was the layman's
organization and uh and then
Presbyterian Churchman United and then
for a while Covenant Fellowship of
Presbyterians, which was a slightly more
broad uh evangelical movement.
I was the chairman of the board of that
organization for a number of years and
um and for a number of years covenant
fellowship was a part of that coalition
as well. As a matter of fact I remember
vividly I think it was 1968 or 69
uh when the leaders of all of those
organizations met at the Hilton Hotel at
the Atlanta airport. That hotel has
since been raised and a beautiful eight
or 10 story hotel is sitting on that
same plot. But I remember we reserved a
a meeting room at that hotel. for we
being the coalition
and uh and our purpose was will we
continue to have an annual fight with
the Southern Presbyterian Church
or we will we agree together that we
need to start something new.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> I was in on that meeting. Ken Smart was
there. Um uh Dr. Nelson Bell was there.
Uh Jack Williamson was there.
>> Uh
All the big names were there and I was
just
>> I'm fast wet behind the ears so to speak
and we spent the whole morning talking
pros and cons about will we continue to
to struggle to try to turn the
denomination the Southern Present church
back toward more faithfulness.
And um
and then we we broke for lunch before we
had lunch. We all got on our knees and
prayed. We broke for lunch and we came
back after lunch and we got on our knees
and prayed again and then we the
commitment was we would pray and then we
would vote and how we voted we would do.
Whatever we decide that one we would
move in that direction and I remember we
got up off of our knees and um uh Dr.
Nelson Bell um stood up and he said,
"Brothers,
I think I know what the outcome of this
is going to be and I want you to know
that I love you and in my heart we will
always be one, but I cannot be a part of
a movement to start a new denomination."
>> Yeah. and um he said, "That's where my
that's where my heart is, and I'm going
to I'm going to leave the room because I
I don't want to be here when the vote
takes place." And Sam Patterson went
with him, who was the first president of
Reform Seminary.
>> And I believe Robert Strong went with
him as well. And uh all of those people
were there. And uh
>> John Richards, who was the pastor of
First Church, Mon was there. And I could
I could go on and on. Yeah.
>> Don Patterson, of course.
>> Uh just read the history books and you
can find their names.
>> Y
>> and um and I um and I voted to leave. I
voted to leave.
>> Mhm.
>> And um
uh and and I
I uh I became very much a part of the
movement. Mhm.
>> We elected at that meeting a committee
of 40. Um Don Patterson and Ken Smart
and Frank Barker and and so forth and so
on were all on and
>> they laid the groundwork and planned all
the meetings that were necessary to
bring the PCA into being in 1973.
>> Yeah. And um
>> but in reality I was I was while I was
personal friends with all of these
people, I was wet behind the ears and
just learning everything I could
learned. And
>> I I was the leader of the PCU PCU, the
President Churchman United movement in
Georgia. And um because I was planting a
church in Georgia in those days and um
and I um and and that church is Chapel
Woods Church, which became a part of the
PCA uh when it was formed, soon after it
was formed. And um and so anyway,
I um I was deeply immersed and greatly
influenced by people like Ken Smart and
uh
>> um Frank Barker and Terry Guyger and Don
Patterson and and um
>> No, Charles, tell me about the the
animating concerns about making that
decision for you and for the others in
the room. What was it that said that led
men to say we need to move forward and
and form something new? What did you
want to see come out of that?
>> Well, the the PCUS PCUS was was on a on
an everinccreasing
um movement.
Um it was increasing in speed toward
toward liberalism. As a matter of fact,
it had already made the decision about
ordaining women. Mhm.
>> Um it had already begun the process of
writing a new confession and discounting
the old historic Westminster confession.
Um it was very committed to the National
Council of Churches and um it was
against the backdrop of the culture in
which we lived. It was woke and it was
more its orthodoxy was defined more in
terms of of the cultural trends than in
terms of and and um than than biblical
theology.
>> Yeah.
And uh so so let me say to you that
um
the PCA as it was formed
was formed
um by a broad big tent uh group of of
leaders and um there were only two or
three whom I would call would be faright
theological
people like Mortyn Smith would be one of
those.
>> Yeah.
>> And um a a godly man, a wonderful man.
He was the first lady clerk of the PCA
and um and he had a big hand in in
putting together the book of church
order that was finally approved by the
first general assembly and um and and a
few others shared this. But people like
Jack Williamson and um
um
and and Frank Barker and Kennedy Smart,
they were more concerned about the
inherence of scripture,
faithfulness to the great commission.
>> Mhm. and and to um
um
and to just sound evangelical doctrine.
Other than Morton Smith and one or two
others, I cannot think of anybody in
that committee of 40 who
who would um
who would be considered a far-right
Calvinist.
>> Mhm.
It was it was really formed as a big it
was big enough for Ben Hayden
who was not
he probably a four-point Calvinist. He
wasn't a fivepoint Calvin Calvinist. Ben
Hayden who was at that time pastor first
church in Chattanooga. And um and it was
big enough for Bruce Dunn uh who was
pastor for years and years and years of
Grace Church Poria
>> and he was a dispensationalist I think
and probably Armenian.
>> Yeah. was big enough for those men to
feel welcomed and uh and to be given a
full voice in the denomination.
>> Yeah. I mean, your your background comes
out of almost sort of a revivalism,
right? The the sort of revival that your
mother became a Christian in. Uh and my
understanding is there's a lot of sort
of Billy Graham evangelicals that were a
part of this coalition.
>> That's right. And and so you're saying
that that there was a sort of broad
evangelicalism and then we want to be
Presbyterian, but there wasn't uh some
of the more uh rigorous Presbyterians
other than Morton Smith and a couple
other guys that you're mentioning at
there at the very beginning.
>> Yeah. For years we um uh after we were
formed um we begin to sense that there
was a a small little movement growing to
to um to merge us with the OPC
>> and um and a group of us began to meet
very concerned about that
>> and um
I um
Jim Baird was very much involved in that
and He was pastor of First Preser Church
in Jackson, Mississippi.
Frank Barker, Kennedy Smart, um, uh,
Terry Guyger, Jack Williamson. Um,
uh, I could
>> What What is What was the concern in
your mind? Like why was that a problem
to think about joining the OPC? Well,
the OPC we saw as rigidly right-wing
when it came to the to u the reformed
faith and um uh they were they were we
saw them as a denomination that was
energized by
theological precision more than they
were energized by evangelism missions.
And this is really the truth. I I I've
been in meetings where Frank Barker
would sometimes say, and I've heard him
say it more than once, "Listen,
brothers,
I'd rather be
uh an evangelical
heretic
than a dead Orthodox."
Mhm.
>> And that was his way of saying, I don't
want to be a part of a denomination that
is not energized by evangelism and
missions.
>> Like the framework of the reformed
faith.
>> Yeah.
>> But I like the fact that there's room
for people on the right, there's room
for people on the left, but we've got to
be led from the center
>> and has to be marked by
um energy for evangelism, a vision for
evangelism and missions and church
plant. and etc. Listen, one of the first
acts of this denomination, uh, Derek,
was to approve a a program where our
mission to the world could have
affiliate relationships with, I think,
50 different parurch mission agencies.
>> Mhm.
>> So people from our churches could become
members of Wicked Bible, Bible
translators, but also have a
relationship with Mission to the World.
>> Yeah.
>> And MAF and
>> Yeah. So there was there was a sort of
broad evangelical coalition that liked
the reform framework and the reformed
faith but didn't want to get caught up
in all the different discussions that
can happen within that reformed
tradition.
>> That's exactly right. And uh we wanted
to have warm cordial relationships with
the NAE National Association of
Evangelicals
um uh the World Reformed Fellowship
um which has has a pretty broad spectrum
of theological perspective. But the PCA,
we felt that the PCA
had a unusual an unusual niche in the
reformed world.
>> Mhm.
>> By our strong commitment to evangelism
and missions.
>> Yeah.
>> And while at the same time
being happily reformed
>> Yeah.
>> reformed framework
>> and committed to the inherency of
scripture.
>> And committed to the inherency of
scripture. But we we were very
aggressively opposed to becoming narrow
and and um and um and I would say um
kind of narrow and um and condemning of
denomination of denominations that
>> well caught up in in various
controversies, you know, within the
tradition. Right.
So a as as the PCA has grown and
developed over the years, how how have
you seen that initial vision
u develop or or remain consistent or get
changed over the years? I mean you've
you were a pastor in the PCA. You are a
pastor in the PCA
>> for our entire history. So you know what
is starting at the founding that's
that's what you saw going on. That's the
conversations you were part of. How has
that changed? How has that stayed the
same uh over the last 50 years?
>> Well, it's
I I would say that we're currently in a
crisis.
From my perspective, we're currently in
a crisis and um um a crisis that I
didn't saw see until we were probably
>> 15 or 20 years into the um into our
history, maybe 25 years.
>> Okay.
history. But gradually, ever so
gradually
um
uh it's become we we found
there's an increasing number of people
who are energized by theological
precision
and who are quick to judge. And I think
the internet has has hurt us badly in
that regard. Uh because we can say bad
things about one another uh without
having to deal with each other, you
know, face to face in in real life in
real time.
>> Yeah.
>> And um but most of the founders
including myself
um were not trained in we weren't
trained at Westminster Seminary. We
weren't trained at a there weren't that
many options. We were trained in in
denominational seminaries that that um
that didn't emphasize
the the narrow finer points of theology.
>> Mhm.
>> And and what we were concerned about was
the fact that they're giving up the
authority of scripture,
>> right?
>> And they're giving up basic things like,
you know, they're redefining missions
and what it they're redefining the
gospel. And I I remember as a as a young
pastor being on the examinations
committee in Atlanta Presbyteria at PCUS
and um a young bright guy came before us
and he was being examined for
ordination. He's going to be ex the
assistant pastor of one of the
prestigious downtown churches in
Atlanta. And and uh I asked him the
question. I said, ' Do you believe
that
a person cannot have his sins forgiven
and have a personal relationship with
God apart from faith, repentance and
faith in Jesus Christ?
And he said, "Yes, I do believe." I say
I believe that a lot of Jewish people
and and and well-meaning people
>> Mhm.
>> who
who um who walk with God and have a a
deep religious relationship with God.
And I said, "Well, then how do you
square that with that passage in the in
John's gospel where Jesus said, "I am
the way, the truth, and the life. No man
cometh to do the Father but by me."
And he thought for a moment and he says,
"Well, in his humanity, Jesus sometimes
overstated his case."
>> And you know, when that when that
committee voted, they voted to approve
his ordination.
>> That was the only only descending vote.
>> Yikes.
>> And then he went to the pres to the
presbyterary Atlanta brethary and I
again was the only descending vote in
the area.
>> And that was a decisive moment for me.
>> Yeah.
So that that gave me a glimpse of what
the future of the PCUS was going to be.
>> Right. Right. So the PCA was formed, you
know, out of concerns of seeing that
happening in the church.
>> It's happening all over.
>> And now you're saying in as you look at
the PCA's history, uh the the focus has
really shifted more towards the
theological position rather than the
let's focus on church planting and
missions from the solid foundation of
inherency and reformed theology. But
it's just getting caught in the weeds is
what it is what you're sounding like
you're saying to me.
>> Yeah, that that that's exactly right.
And I I think that
you know in our recent general
assemblies, there's been an increasing
reason to be concerned. I think in terms
of the the spirit of the assembly and um
the issues that are before us and um and
we're finding the assembly itself to
make decisions and pass over to us that
we now have to struggle in the
presbyterist to keep from being enacted,
you know.
>> Yeah.
>> As a part of the denominations
um founding documents.
>> Yeah. So, I'm going to I'm going to um
ask this question kind of trying to
voice some of the concerns I hear from
the right side of the denomination. I
mean, you talked about the things going
on in the PCUs that that raised concerns
and led to the founding of the PCA. I
think a lot of guys would acknowledge
that we're not there. I mean, there's
nobody in the PCA saying that that you
can find salvation outside of Christ. I
mean, that's not going on. We're not
strictly liberal. But I I think some
guys are afraid that we're moving in
that direction or we're getting more
caught up in um in social activism or
cultural concerns that are taking the
the the eye off of a a sound
conservative theology. How I mean, how
would you respond to those guys that are
raising those concerns? Um,
>> yeah, I've been in the PCA from the very
beginning and um and I I can honestly
say
I do not know of a of a liberal in the
PCA.
Now, there have been some who've become
liberal who are now outside of the PCA
and uh but the the PCA is a very sound
doctrinal denomination.
But the PCA has always been concerned
about
evangelism and always been concerned
a dimension of evangelism that
uh that focuses on
which includes a division of evangelism
that focuses on um the marginalized
folks
and um the people who are being
mistreated are are aren't experiencing
justice are who dying of hunger or
>> lack of medical care etc. And and I
think I think the far right of the
church is scared to death of the social
side
of the of gospel implications.
>> Okay. And um
and and I think as the culture becomes
more secular and more dark and we're
dealing with with issues like human
sexuality and all kinds of deviations
from biblical descriptions of proper
human sexuality. I think there's a fear
on the on on the right that the
denomination is going to drift there.
>> Yeah.
>> I have no fear of that.
I I think I think our understanding of
the power of the gospel is so great that
um that um
that in my lifetime which probably isn't
very much longer but in my lifetime I
will never never see the denomination
wrestle with those issues.
>> Yeah. Yeah. We do we do we we are and
another thing that is an issue is is I
think that we have a great variety of
worship styles in the PCA and and
there's a a movement of foot I think uh
to unify
um our worship styles so that we all
worshiping the same way perhaps even
using a lectionary and and that kind of
a thing becoming uh becoming more
more unified in terms of what the
worship service looks like from church
to church to church to church. And I
think that scares a lot of people on the
far right as well.
>> And then closely related to it is the
women's issue.
>> And
it it troubles me that
uh the far right appears to subjugate
uh women. They don't want to see women
um have any kind of leadership roles in
the life of the church.
>> And um and
Let me let me tell you that's that's a
major hurdle. Tim Keller wrestled with
that. But the far right doesn't like the
way he came out of it. You know, the way
he settled that issue and York.
>> Yeah. I mean, it does seem like there's
a lot of concern about things that did
happen in the PCUs, you know, eventually
happening in the PCA, and this seen as a
slide in that direction and and a desire
to have a more
>> thoroughly or or consistent reformed
theology worked out throughout our
churches. That does seem to be an
animating concern on one side of the
denomination. It sounds like what you're
saying though is the PCA was formed with
a a concern to to be conservative, to
believe the Bible, to to believe in the
um the unique salvation that Christ
alone can offer on the one hand, but
also to not dive so heavily into
reformed theology that we end up being
only focused on theological precision,
more like the OPC. Like both of those
were um were errors or or directions
that the PCA founders wanted to avoid.
Yeah, I think that that kind of sums it
up very well. Uh Derek, I
I finally concluded that
the real issue
uh is what is it that energizes you
as as a leader in the church? Is it is
it theological precision or is it being
faithful to the great commission?
And I think from from from that dividing
point, I think there's a
a concern on my part that the people who
are energized by theology are going to
take me to a legalistic
narrow sectarian place
that I think loses contact with culture.
>> Yeah.
and uh it makes it virtually impossible
to to communicate to culture and to
>> and to make the gospel understandable
and applicable to the culture.
>> Yeah.
>> And and I think their concern is that
>> that we will we will apply the gospel in
such a way as to
as to um ultimately come become like the
denomination we left.
>> Yeah. I think the thing that anchors us
is our commitment to the great
commission and to the gospel.
>> That's that's our anchor.
>> And um so I I think we agree on the
essentials. We disagree
on the on the non-essentials or at least
the the things that
um that should not divide us.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, um, if I'm, if I'm going
to try to represent, you know, voices
I've heard in our denomination, I think,
you know, a lot of them on the right
would say we we care deeply about
evangelism and missions, but we think,
you know, theological precision is is
necessary to do that, you know, properly
and well. And I think others of us are
saying, yeah, that's true, but to a
certain extent, there's a lot of
questions that we don't have to be
united on in order to partner in mission
and evangelism effectively. And I just
think of your own story and your mom,
you know, going to a primitive Baptist
church revival and getting saved and uh
and you know we God doesn't need our
theological precision to be effective in
evangelism. And so there's a certain
sense in which the denomination is kind
of wrestling with where that boundary
needs to be like how much do we need to
agree on to do partnership and mission
and evangelism. Um and some want a lot
more agreement and others think that
there can be more breadth within the
reformed tradition. So that seems to be
what we're struggling with and in some
ways that's that's the struggle uh that
that was there right there at the
beginning with some of the the options
that the PCA had before them. Does that
sound fair to you?
>> Yeah, I think that's very fair. And I I
think that says well the uh the current
state of affairs in the in the
denomination
but but I will say this that
the founding fathers
which I don't cons consider myself to be
one of us. I was an Aaron boy founding
fathers.
>> I wasn't a um I wasn't a um a major
mover in all of that.
But I do have a good memory of of uh how
they struggled and um
and and and I would say that our
concerns
were not those concerns. And and I
believe honestly honestly with my heart,
I believe that Frank Barker would say
that if he were alive today and Jim B
would say that if he were alive today.
And um uh I mean the Broadwood Church
under his leadership
um often walks very close to the edge
in terms of of their youth ministry, of
their medical ministry, of of their
campus ministry, campus outreach, etc.
and um uh and
under his leadership, Brianwood kind of
modeled
um in the in the very best sense the
great diversity
and the our willingness to to go to the
edges so to speak and and and have
ministry in the to the culture. started
a a seminary that was really birthed out
of a concern to see black pastors
trained in sound doctrine
>> which is still going today. Browwood
Broadway Seminary.
>> Yeah. And um I I I I
pray that we will not allow the
denomination to drift into
a far-right
very very dogmatic driven
um theologically
>> denomination
because quite frankly historically they
don't thrive
and um and they're more about what they
don't believe than what they do believe.
And u I think there's a there's a
there's a culture out there that
desperately needs the gospel.
>> Uh there are people who are struggling
with samesex attraction, people who are
struggling with their identity, sexual
identity that we need to be in
conversation with.
>> Mhm. And and we need to instead of being
seen as a denomination of haters,
we need to be seen as a denomination of
lovers.
>> Yeah.
>> And u and that doesn't mean approving
sin.
>> Right. Right.
>> It means winning the right to have
conversations and to share the good news
of the gospel, which transforms and sets
you free from uh the things that the far
right is afraid of.
And uh
>> yeah, I I think you know, one of our
strengths now, it seems as a
denomination is we're we have a lot of
sort of the theologically robust uh men
and women who think deeply about God's
word and our confession. And um I'd love
to see some of that rigor directed
towards a lot of the emerging questions
that um we're going to be facing in the
future about things like AI and
reproductive technologies and just a
whole host of really complicated issues
that the reform tradition hasn't spoken
to directly, right? because it's not the
the context in which the reformed
tradition was sort of emerged. And so,
um, it'd be great if if for the sake of
mission and engaging our culture, that
was some of the the energy that we um we
extended towards those questions.
>> Well, I I really believe, Derek, that
the PCA offers that to the reformed
world.
>> Yeah. I think we were born in such a way
and that we were the the um our
foundation allowed us to uh to be
faithful but on the cutting edge.
>> Yeah.
>> And and u and you know what we have a
pretty good track record of writing some
very good papers and study papers and
documents
>> uh that isn't just a rehash of of things
that would have been said aundred years
ago or even 50 years ago. and and and
we've had a
uh our history is when we disagree,
we get our best thinkers together to
think it out and to write a document and
that kind of settles the matter for us.
>> Yeah.
>> And uh if we stop talking to one another
>> and do all our talking on the internet
or through social media platforms,
I I fear to think of what would happen
to the denomination, right?
>> Yeah. uh uh
we've always we've always had good
dialogue and uh and and it's and we've
always given each other lots of freedom
and um and I would I would like to see
where um
uh redeemer churches in New York would
be as applauded as the most um socially
conservative church in the denomination.
maybe First Church, Jackson, Mississippi
or or somewhere else. I'm not sure where
they would be, but but you know what I'm
talking about. I
>> Yeah.
>> And u Paul Cor one time said to me as he
talks to his his friends who are more
right than he is, he said, "You know,
the problem is the denomination that you
envision
is not big enough for me.
you would not allow a man like me to be
in your denomination
because I want to give women more
visibility in the life of the church. Uh
I want to make better use of their
gifts. But um you're afraid of that? M
>> and um and the PCA up until this point
has I think been a unique reformed
denomination
faithful to scripture, faithful to the
great commission and also faithful to
the reformed faith. But the highest
priority is not the reformed faith. The
highest priority is scripture and
evangelism and missions.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh so I um
Hey, listen. I'm I love the PCA and and
I I um I'm doing everything I can
uh from my present position to
um to see um to see us be a healthy and
united denomination. And that's why I'm
very willing to talk with you today on
this podcast.
>> Yeah. Well, I'm I'm really grateful for
your time today, Charles, and for your
ministry in the PCA um for the last 50
years, and I'm thankful that you'd share
your story with us a little bit and your
experience, not only at the founding,
but even up to today. So, thanks for
taking the time and um I'm going to I'm
going to end here and just note to those
who are listening still um that we hope
to have some more conversations like
this uh and maybe even conversations
with differing perspectives on some of
the the questions and the issues that
that Charles was raising that our
denomination is facing. So, thanks
everyone for your time.